<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on T. Ben Thompson</title>
    <link>http://tbenthompson.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on T. Ben Thompson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://tbenthompson.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>DRAFT! Automated testing for scientists and data analysts</title>
      <link>http://tbenthompson.com/post/automated_testing_for_science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tbenthompson.com/post/automated_testing_for_science/</guid>
      <description>A lot of scientists and data analysts don&amp;rsquo;t use automatic test suites for verifying their code. And, I think that&amp;rsquo;s because it&amp;rsquo;s really hard. Almost all the introductions to automated testing that I&amp;rsquo;ve seen come from a more typical software engineering perspective. They assume you already know exactly what the output of your code should be. And the trouble with science is that that&amp;rsquo;s rarely the case. I mean, if you know the results ahead of time, we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be doing science!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sneaky (transparent) huge pages</title>
      <link>http://tbenthompson.com/post/sneaky-transparent-huge-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tbenthompson.com/post/sneaky-transparent-huge-pages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sparse n-body matrices</title>
      <link>http://tbenthompson.com/post/sparse_nbody/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tbenthompson.com/post/sparse_nbody/</guid>
      <description>This is a sparsity plot of a matrix representing an approximate n-body interaction. The black dots are non-zeros in the matrix. Imagine 2000 stars, each exerting some gravitational pull on each of the other stars. This gravitational interaction could be represented by a dense matrix:
$$ A_{ij} = \frac{G m_i m_j}{|\mathbf{x}_i - \mathbf{x}_j|^2} $$
This works, but dense matrices can be slow when there are many stars. The cost of evaluating a matrix-vector product will scale like $O(n^2)$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up my website</title>
      <link>http://tbenthompson.com/post/setting_up_website/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tbenthompson.com/post/setting_up_website/</guid>
      <description>I have a website now. Since technical stuff is fun, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d share the way I set it up.
The site is a set of statically served HTML pages. Hugo makes this really easy. Hugo is super fast and is written in Go. You can set up a few template pages and then write posts and pages in Markdown. Some layout is also done using Go templates. Running Hugo takes your templates and pages and concerts them into static HTML.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>